Guide to the
Brown University Library
Default Call Number
John Hay Library University Archives and Manuscripts Box A Brown University Providence, RI, 02912 Telephone: Manuscripts: 401-863-3723; University Archives: 401-863-2148 Email: Manuscripts: hay@brown.edu; University Archives: archives@brown.edu
Biographical/Historical Note
Collection information
There are no restrictions on access, except that the collection can only be seen by prior appointment. Some materials may be stored off-site and cannot be produced on the same day on which they are requested.
Series I. Corporation records (Minutes)
Series II. Reports, etc. for Corporation Records
Series III. Corporation proceedings and reports
Series IV. Advisory and Executive Committee minutes and reports
Series V. Advisory and Executive Committee Minutes
Series VI. Advisory and Executive Committee .title Reports
Series VII. Corporation correspondence
Series VII. Correspondence
- Corporation records (Minutes), Series I
  - Brown University--Corporation Records, 1764-1904
    Records. volumes. v.1: Charter; minutes, September, 1764 to September 6, 1810 - v.2: Form of engagement; minutes, September 6, 1810 to September 7, 1843 - v.3: Form of engagement; charter; minutes, September 3, 1844 to June 17, 1875 - v.4: Form of engagement; minutes, September 1, 1875 to September 6, 1893; v.5: Minutes, June 19, 1895 to April 28, 1904. Originals in vault. Negative photostats (8 volumes) BOUND-1.
- Reports, etc. for Corporation Records, Series II
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1925-1926
    Reports and other material from which the Board of Fellows and Corporation records are composed, volume 1.
- Corporation proceedings and reports, Series III
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1764-1772
    Proceedings of the Corporation from 1764 to 1770 [i.e. 1772] .... ---.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1861
    [Extracts from Corporation records, 1794-1861, compiled by Reuben A. Guild]. n.d. References to: Established of University Grammar School (1794, 1809); Naming the College (1795, 1803); Student attendance at church (1798, 1801); Funds of the College (1821, 1826); Professor Gammell to prepare history of the College (1844); Aid to indigent students (1846); Nicholas Brown scholarships (1846, 1858); Faculty salaries (1848); Resignation of Dr. Wayland (1849); Presentation of Hopkins chair (1849); Election of Dr. Sears as President (1855); Boading in Clubs (1857); Change in degree requirements (1857), Gift of Bowen Estate by John Carter Brown (1860); Aid fund established by Miss Lydia Carpenter (1861);.
- Advisory and Executive Committee minutes and reports, Series IV
  - Brown University--Corporation--Executive board, 1851-1856,1858-1860,1862-1865
    Reports .... A18079-86,35444[5]. Thirteen reports.
- Advisory and Executive Committee Minutes, Series V
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Minutes, 1906 September 14 (Folder V.1)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Minutes, 1907 January 11 (Folder V.2)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Minutes, 1908 May 08 (Folder V.3)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Minutes, 1909 June 04 (Folder V.4)
- Advisory and Executive Committee .title Reports, Series VI
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1869 September 02 (Folder VI.1)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1870 April 04 (Folder VI.2)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1871 June 29 (Folder VI.3)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1875 (Folder VI.4)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1878 (Folder VI.5)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1880 (Folder VI.6)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1889 (Folder VI.7)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1890 June 19 (Folder VI.8)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1890 September 03 (Folder VI.9)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1891 September 02 (Folder VI.10)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1891 June 18 (Folder VI.11)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1892 June 23 (Folder VI.12)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1892 October 07 (Folder VI.13)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1892 November 30 (Folder VI.14)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1893 June 29 (Folder VI.15)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1893 September 06 (Folder VI.16)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1894 June 20 (Folder VI.17)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1894 September 05 (Folder VI.18)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1895 June 20 (Folder VI.19)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1895 September 04 (Folder VI.20)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1897 June 17 (Folder VI.21)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1897 September 01 (Folder VI.22)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1898 June 16 (Folder VI.23)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1898 September 07 (Folder VI.24)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1899 June 07 (Folder VI.25)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1899 September 06 (Folder VI.26)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1900 March 20 (Folder VI.27)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1900 June 21 (Folder VI.28)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1901 June 20 (Folder VI.29)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1901 September 04 (Folder VI.30)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1902 June 19 (Folder VI.31)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1902 September 03 (Folder VI.32)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1903 June 18 (Folder VI.33)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1903 September 02 (Folder VI.34)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1904 June 16 (Folder VI.35)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1905 June 22 (Folder VI.36)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1905 October 04 (Folder VI.37)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1906 June 21 (Folder VI.38)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1906 October 03 (Folder VI.39)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1907 June 20 (Folder VI.40)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1908 June 18 (Folder VI.41)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1908 October 21 (Folder VI.42)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1909 March 02 (Folder VI.43)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1909 June 17 (Folder VI.44)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1909 October 06 (Folder VI.45)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1909 October 13 (Folder VI.46)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1910 November 10 (Folder VI.47)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1912 June 20 (Folder VI.48)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1912 October 09 (Folder VI.49)
  - Brown University--Corporation--Advisory and Executive Committee Report, 1913 June 19 (Folder VI.50)
- Corporation correspondence, 1913 December 18; Series VII (Folder VI.51)
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1768 January 17
    Vote of a Com[mitt]ee of the Corporation ... respecting a Memor[ia]l to the G[enera]l Assembly of Scotland for Donat[io]ns to ye College .... A20598.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1769 August 19
    [Subscription list for the purchase of an electrical apparatus for the College] .... A20512.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1769 December 23
    [Subscription for locating the proposed college of the colony of Rhode Island in Newport and account of meeting in Court House in Newport December 23, 1769] .... A20953-4. Copy by Sarah K. Birckhead. Includes copy of letter referring to Stiles Charter. With this is letter from Sarah K. Birckhead to Walter C. Bronson concerning the documents.
  - Ward, Henry, 1732-1797, 1769 December 30
    Certificate ... concerning ye Newpt. Subscription .... A20506. Prospect of increasing subscription for placing the College in Newport. Signed by Henry Ward and Edward Thurston.
  - Brown University, 1770 February 06
    [List of subscribers to a fund to locate the college west of Weybosset Bridge] .... A13219.
  - Hart, Oliver, 1723-1795, 1770 May 16
    To [Hezekiah] Smith .... A9407. Discusses church news, and mention several Baptist clergymen: Gano, Edwards, Manning.
  - Maxwell, Adam, 1770 September 04
    To David Howell .... A1561. Sends "some very imperfect specimens of my writing.".
  - Brown University, 1772 May 13, 1803 August
    [Account with Joseph and William Russell] .... A21140. Note added by committee to settle the account, August, 1803.
  - Vigneron, Walter (1776), 1773?
    [Contract] .... A14750. Requiring Walter Vigneron to pay William Holroyd, steward, for tuition, board at Commons, and room rent.
  - Brown University--Class of 1773, 1773 February 19
    The remonstrance of the Senior Class of Rhode Island College, to the respectable, the President and Professor of the same .... A21211. Copy in handwriting of Solomon Drowne. Signed by Jacob Nash, Henry Tillinghast, Joseph Litchfield. Urging a public commencement for the class.
  - Brown University, 1773-1774
    [Draft of text of diploma for honorary degrees] .... A17456. Contains list of English recipients of honorary degrees, 1773-74.
  - Pelot, Francis, 1720-1774, 1774 February 24
    To Stephen Hopkins, James Manning and the Committee of the. Corporation of the college in Providence .... A12340. Written from Ewhaw, S.C. Discussing his efforts to raise funds for the college.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1775?
    [Regulation prohibiting the use of spirituous liquor in the College and of entertainment in student rooms[ .... A18502.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1780 May 06
    [Petition to Congress to repair the College] .... A17325. Asks that damage done by troops be repaired at public expense. With this, true copy of petition to Congress as laid before the General Assembly of R. I. with resolves of the Assembly thereon. Attested by David Howell.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1780?
    [Vote passed by Corporation] .... A17257. In handwriting of David Howell, secretary. Voted that a committee inspect and supervise the College Edifice during its occupancy by troops and that no further alterations be made without approval of the Committee.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1782 May 31
    [Minutes of meeting] .... A17324. Appointing committees to remove buildings from College Lot, to rent rooms in the College, and to ascertain damage done to College Edifice by the American and French armies.
  - Brown, Nicholas, 1729-1791, 1782 September 05
    [Subscription for repairing the College Edifice] .... A17249. Also signed by John Brown. On verso is note by Joseph Brown, May 12, 1783, receipt for payment of subscriptions.
  - Brown University--Corporation--Committee on damages to the college edifice, 1782 June 12
    [Estimate of damages to the college edifice during the Revolutionary War] .... A17248. Signed, Jona. Hammon, William Wheaton, Jno. Dorrance. Autograph note added and signed by Daniel Cooke, Justice of the Peace, April 30, 1785. With this, an unsigned copy of the document.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1782, 1804, 1844, 1862
    [Excerpts from Corporation records relating to form of "engagment" for installation of Fellows and Trustees] .... A18245.
  - Brown University--Department of sciences, 1783?
    A short description of the Micrometer, and of the Reflecting telescope .... A18510-11. Instruments purchased for the use of the classes in science, ca. 1783.
  - Wilkinson, William, 1760-1852 (1783), 1783 September 25
    To David Howell .... A1563. Reports on progress at school of young Jeremiah Howell.
  - Brown University--Department of sciences, 1783
    [Draft of remaining parts of an Apparatus for the College] ... A9411.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1784-1795
    [Extracts from early records of the Corporation] .... A9418. Concerning resignations and elections of Fellows and Trustees.
  - Brown, John, 1736-1803, 1784 January 27
    To Corporation of Brown University .... A21634-5. Submitting his treasurer's report, 1775-1784. With this, receipt, John Brown to committee to adjust his accounts, January 27, 1784.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1784 September 09
    To His Most Christian Majesty [Louis XVI] .... A20610. Copy signed by Stephen Hopkins and James Manning, asking assistance in procuring collection of French authors and establishing a professorship of French language and history.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1785 February 17, 1792 August 13
    [Votes to apply to Congress for reparation for occupation of and damage to the college during the war] .... A17327. Extracts from Corporation records. Witnessed by David Howell, secretary.
  - Lawrence, Joseph, 1785 April 30
    [Document relating to use of College for Army Barracks] .... A17323. Certifies that the College was used as barracks from December 10, 1776 to August 20, 1779 without compensation for rent or damages. On verso, certification of Lawrence's appointment as Barracks Master in December 1776, signed by Jabez Bowen. With this, copy of Lawrence's document.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1785 May 03
    [Petition to Congress to repair the College] .... A17326. Copy. Asking compensation for damages done by troops. Describes the College Edifice.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1785 May 03
    The United States of America to Rhode Island College, Dr. .... A17318. Bill for rent and damages to College during its occupation by troops.
  - Brown, Nicholas, 1729-1791, 1786 April 02
    To Hezekiah Smith .... A9447. Urges him to come to Providence to supply pulpit Manning has gone to Congress hoping to get what is due the College for damages, as the college funds are not sufficient to maintain him; also, as the College increases, Manning is not able to perform duties of both president and pastor; seeks his advice on procuring a new pastor; 15 students to enroll in fall.
  - Foster, William, 1786 June 28
    To [Perez] Fobes .... A20916. Concerns instruments he ordered from London suggests insurance on the instruments. With this, bill listing items.
  - Brown University--Class of 1788
    To the honorable Corporation .... A21212. Petition signed by twenty members of the class, requesting seats on the stage at Commencement. On verso are miscellaneous notes and quotations in the hand of Solomon Drowne.
  - Drowne, Solomon, 1753-1834 (1773), 1791
    To Doctors Jonathan Easton and Isaac Senter. Signed also by William Bowen and David Howell. Requesting aid of Easton and Senter in a case involving the life of President Manning.
  - Flint, Abel, 1763-1825, 1791 March
    To Enos Hitchcock .... A10335. Urging him and Mrs. Hitchcock to be present at his ordination.
  - Bowen, Jabez, 1739-1815, 1791 July 29
    To the Corporation .... A6608. List of Corporation members. Meeting called to make arrangements for funeral of James Manning and to discuss problems of the college.
  - Howell, David, 1747-1824, 1791 July 30
    [Obituary notice of James Manning] .... A21578.
  - Flint, Abel, 1763-1825, 1791 August 04
    To [Enos Hitchcock] .... A10334. Announcing his marriage and commenting on Manning's death.
  - Flint, Abel, 1763-1825, 1791 October 03
    To [Enos Hitchcock] .... A10333. Comments on choice of president of the college and on ordination of Mr. Leonard.
  - Pitman, John, 1785-1864 (1799), 1791 October 03
    To Robert Carter .... A7190. Writes of death of James Manning, and expresses the hope that Carter will still send his son George to the college.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1792 December 06
    [Petition to Congress for damages and rent of the Edifice] .... A17328. Describes the College Edifice and tells use of it during the Revolution.
  - Bowen, Jabez, 1739-1815, 1792 December 12
    [Certification that the College was evacuated by French troops on May 27, 1782] .... A17322. Draft on verso.
  - Bowen, Jabez, 1739-1815, 1792 December 12
    To Benjamin Bourne .... A17321. To representative in Congress from Rhode Island, concerning claims to Congress for damages to the College during its occupation by troops.
  - Bowen, Jabez, 1739-1815, 1792 December 12
    To Theodore Foster and Joseph Stanton .... A17320. Copy of letter to senators from Rhode Island asking help in presenting claims to Congress for use of the College by troops.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1792 December 13
    The United States of America to Rhode Island College, Dr.. Bill for rent and damages. The 1785 bill with interest to 1792 added.
  - Prince, John, 1751-1836, 1794 July 22
    To Loammi Baldwin .... A9593. Informs him that they have been appointed to inspect Mr. Fobes's philosophical instruments.
  - Brown University, 1794 September
    [Commencement program] .... A12255. With list of orators.
  - Maxcy, Jonathan, 1768-1820 (1787), 1795 July 12
    To [Richard Furman] .... A10332. Concerning position at the college and his religious views.
  - Prince, John, 1751-1836, 1795 August 20
    To Loammi Baldwin .... A9592. Committee of the Academy to inspect Dr. Fobes's instruments.
  - Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804, 1795 January 31
    [Report on petition of the Corporation of Rhode Island College] .... A32498. On claims of the College for damage to the College Edifice during its occupation by American and French troops.
  - Rogers, William, 1751-1824 (1769), 1795
    [Sermon preached on the death of Rev. Morgan Edwards] .... A9227. In handwriting of Rogers. With this, a typescript giving information about Rogers and Edwards.
  - Maxcy, Jonathan, 1768-1820 (1787), 1796 April 11
    To Welcome Arnold .... A11187. Requests indulgence in the paying of amounts due on a note, explaining his difficulties in collecting money owed him.
  - Bowen, Jabez, 1739-1815, 1796 April 27
    To Sir .... A10337. States that application for compensation for use of the Edifice has been made directly to the Congress; No recompense has been made, although institutions in Delaware, Princeton and Cambridge have been compensated for rents and damages.
  - Allen, Bridgham J., 1797?
    To James Fenner .... A11176. Bill for copying done. Includes charge for two college lottery tickets ($12. for tickets numbered 211 and 212).
  - Brown University--Committee for the college lottery, 1798-1801
    [Accounts] .... A20862-81. Accounts with John Whipple and Samuel Thurber, managers of the College Lottery. Includes promissory notes and receipts.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1798 May 12
    [Report of committee on encroachments on the college land] .... A20507. Reports five cases of encroachment on college lands.
  - Fobes, Perez, 1742-1812, 1799?
    [Account for philosophical instruments made and imported] .... A20633. On last page is note of salary received from the college.
  - Wilkinson, William, 1760-1852 (1783), 1799 December 24
    To Benjamin Bourne .... A34993. Announces the death of George Washington.
  - Burgess, Thomas, 1799? March 20
    To Benjamin Bourne .... A11200.
  - Brown, James 1761-1834 (1780), 1800 March 14
    To B[enjamin] Bourne .... A12253. States decision of Corporation to dismiss Bourne's son and a number of others.
  - United States--Treasury Department, 1800 May 06
    [Certificate of account between U.S. and Rhode Island College] .... A17319. Sum of $2779.13 due the College for use by troops and damages.
  - Smith, Hezekiah, 1737-1805, 1801 October 26
    To Jonathan Maxcy .... A9420. Comments on the choice of Maxcy as president of Union College.
  - Brown University, 1801?
    Amt. of the certificates which are funded in the Secry's office belonging to the college .... A20379.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1804 September 06
    [Report of a committee to examine accounts of Dr. John Prince] .... A21199. Signed by Robert Rogers and Samuel Eddy. Note by David Howell added. Receipt on last page.
  - Brown University--Corporation, 1806?
    References to votes etc. .... A18512. Notations from reports of the Corporation from 1768 to 1806.
  - Brown University, 1805
    Brown University in account with Perez Fobes .... A18524.
  - Fobes, Perez, 1742-1812, 1806 September 02
    To the Corporation .... A7198. Explaining adjustments of a claim for apparatus.
  - Brown University--Class of 1806, 1806 September 04, 1908 August 21
    To the Secretary of the Corporation .... A8038. Request of the senior class for permission to invite Providence Company of Cadets to attend procession at Commencement. Also signed by Jacob Hill and Adoniram Judson. See Frances Wayland papers, box 7, folder 89, Emily (Cuddeback) Judson. RJB 8/21/08.
  - Clarke, Abraham Lynsen, 1808 November
    To Moses Lippitt .... A7196. Resignation as Fellow.
  - Arnold, Thomas, 1808 February 13
    To [Moses] Brown .... A9541. Thinks Brown's accusations against students for attending and performing theatricals unjust and suggests he acknowledge his mistake.
  - Lippitt, Moses, 1810 June 06
    To Thomas P. Ives .... A7995. Sending check for amount of schoolhouse subscription balance. List of names on verso.
  - Flint, Abel, 1763-1825, 1812 May 05
    To dear Sir .... A10336. Written to a college president at the request of Oliver D. Cooke, a bookseller in Hartford, asking him to take his son as a boarder.
  - Griswold, Alexander Viets, 1766-1843, 1812 September 23
    To Samuel Eddy .... A7195. Accepting election as Fellow.
  - Brown and Ives, 1812 November
    To Moses Lippitt .... A7998. Concerns subscription papers for University Grammar School.
  - Sterry, Cyprian, 1813 August 31
    To Jabez Bowen .... A7202. Resigns from Corporation.
  - Burrill, James, 1772-1820 (1788), 1813 September 06
    To Samuel Eddy .... A7200. Accepts appointment as trustee.
  - Dorr, Sullivan, 1778-1858, 1813 September 09
    To Samuel Eddy .... A7338. Accepts election as trustee.
  - Mason, Amasa, 1813 September 13
    To Samuel Eddy .... A7201. Accepts election as trustee.
  - Secomb, Ebenezer, 1814 August 06
    To Samuel Eddy .... A7203. Accepts election as trustee.
  - Mackie, John, 1815 October 19
    To the Corporation .... A7205. Declines professorship of chemistry.
  - Ingalls, William, 1769-1851 (h1813), 1816 August 03
    To the Fellows of Corporation of Brown University .... A2374. Resigns his professorship.